（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）
頭では分かっているのに
動けないのは何でだ
I understand it in my head, so why can I do nothing about it?
“勝つ理由が無い”とか言いながら
負けると苦しいのは なぜだ
I say I have no reason to win,
so why is it so painful when I lose?
I always take half-measures...
中途半端だ 僕は
何もかも
with everything.
I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
Child of God (Part Three) Continued
Stare
見てる… めっちゃ見てるよ
He's staring at me. He's totally staring at me!
デカい… 怖い…
He's huge... I'm scared!
Um... what's your name?
（高橋(たかはし)勇介(ゆうすけ)）
あの… お名前は？
はっ
ああ あの… 桐山です
U-Um... I'm Kiriyama.
下の名は？
And your first name?
あっ 零です
It's Rei. Kiriyama Rei.
桐山零
ああ… やっぱりそうだ
I thought so.
You became a professional shogi player in junior high.
あの中学生で
将棋のプロになった
Nice to meet you. I'm Takahashi Yuusuke.
はじめまして 高橋勇介です
Huh?
僕は野球をやっていて
I play baseball and hope to turn pro in the future.
将来はプロになれたらと
思っているんです
I wasn't sure if I should rely on a baseball
scholarship to get into a local high school,
で この先—
このまま 都内の高校に
野球推薦で入るか
or go to a rural school that has a chance at going to nationals.
確実に
甲子園を狙える—
地方の高校に行くかで
迷っていたら—
Then, my dad told me about you.
父が あなたのこと
話してくれたんです
In this world, there are kids like him who decided
their own path in junior high and then turned pro.
（勇介の父）
世の中には この子みたいに
中学生でバシッと
自分の道を決めて
プロになったヤツも
ちゃんといるんだ
If you want to become a pro,
you need to be courageous and make a decision.
プロになりたければ
ちゃんと自分で勇気を出して選べ
So I decided to go to a high school in Shikoku.
（勇介）それで 俺—
四国の高校に
行くことに決めたんです
A coach who helped me at a junior tournament invited me.
ジュニアの大会でお世話になった
監督が誘ってくれているので
But I wanted to ask you something first.
でも 聞きたかったんです
桐山さんはプロになってから
１年遅れで—
After turning pro, you went back to high school a year later, right?
また学校に行かれてますよね
あの… それは どうしてですか？
Um, why did you do that?
（零）彼の真剣な顔を見て
これは うわべの答えではなくて
Looking at his serious expression,
I realized that this was a question that needed more than a superficial answer.
ほんとの言葉を探して
答えないといけない質問だと
It needed sincere words.
そう理解した
でも—
But...
何て伝えたらいいだろう
what should I convey to him?
Um...
ええっと…
僕は本当に
将棋にしか特化してないんです
I really only specialize in shogi.
I'm not really good at socializing.
人づきあいも苦手だし
I like studying, but I couldn't fit in at school.
勉強は好きだけど
学校には なじめませんでした
I don't regret deciding on the direction of my life so early.
人生を早く決めたことは
後悔していません
But...
でも… 多分—
I think I wanted memories of not running away.
逃げなかったって記憶が
欲しかったんだと思います
Probably.
（零）うわぁ
は… 恥ずかしくなってきた
N-Now I'm getting embarrassed!
Why am I giving a speech like this?
俺 何 語っちゃってるんだ？
こんな 初めて会った
中学生相手に
He's a junior high student whom I just met.
Blush
I see.
そうか
（高橋）逃げたり
サボったりした記憶って
Only I will know my own memories of "running away" and "slacking off,"
自分にしか分からないけど
あ ピンチの時に
よく監督に
but at critical moments,
my coach often tells me to "believe in myself."
自分を信じろって
言われるんスけど
However, if you have even one memory of
"running away" or "slacking off,"
でも 自分の中に
ちょっとでも
逃げたり サボったりした
記憶があると
you'd think, "But I totally slacked off that other time."
いや だって 俺—
あのときサボったし
って思っちゃって
それができないんです
And then, you can't do it.
Anyway, I can't explain it well,
だから…
うまく言えないけど
but you wanted to get rid of things like that, right?
そういうの無くしたかった
ってことですよね
It got through.
（零）通じた
Yeah.
Oh no...
（零）ヤバイ
What is this?
何だこれ すっごいうれしい
I'm really happy.
It felt like...
何だか 油断すると
if I let my guard down,
うっかり 涙が出そうで焦った
tears would stream down my face, so I panicked.
そのくらい うれしかった
That's how happy I was.
（男子１）
あっ おーい 高橋
Hey, Takahashi!
Sorry we're late. Let's go!
（男子２）
遅れてすまん 行こうぜ
Right.
Oh, but I wanted to talk a little more...
あっ でも俺…
まだ もうちょっと…
Um, if you don't mind, let's talk again.
あの… よかったら また話そう
え？ いいんスか？
Is that okay?
You can get in touch with me through Hina...
I mean Kawamoto.
ヒナちゃん…
川本さん通して連絡くれれば
Okay, got it.
そうっスか
I'll call you soon, Kawamoto.
じゃあ よろしくな 川本
R-Right!
Shrivel
Thump
Thank you, Hina!
Thank you, Kiriyama!
（零）ありがとう ヒナちゃん
（ひなた）ありがとう 桐山君
He's kind of a cool guy.
何か 彼 かっこいいね
でしょ？
すっごく しっかりしているの
I know, right?
He's really got his act together.
So, what did you two talk about?
で 何 話したの？ ２人で
（零）え？ ああ… ええっと
Huh? Well, uh...
Pshnore... Pshnore... Ps...
（シロちゃん）時が… 見える
I can see the flow of time...
Thank you for the meal!
（あかり･ひなた･モモ）
ごちそうさまでした！
Let's see...
（川本あかり）
えっと えっと…
I made salted rice balls out of all the rice.
ごはんは みんな
塩むすびにしといたよ
There's also tempura, a boiled egg, pickled vegetables...
あとは
天ぷらとゆで卵とお漬物と
Thank you. I really appreciate it.
（零）すみません 助かります
零ちゃん ありがとー
Thanks, Rei!
See you later!
またねー
That night, the warm dinner and the events of the day made my stomach feel fluffy.
（零）その夜は
温かいごはんと
いろんな出来事で
おなかの中が ふわふわして
I couldn't fall sleep easily,
なかなか眠くならなくて
遅くまで 詰め将棋の問題を
延々解き続けた
so I stayed up late solving shogi checkmate problems.
ふと気づくと
Suddenly, the smell of the water and the sound of the waves climbed up to my room on the sixth floor.
６階の僕の部屋まで
水の匂いと波の音が
のぼってきていた
I wanted to ask you.
聞いてみたかったんです
（零）彼が僕に聞いたように
Just like how he asked me,
if a day comes when I'm able to ask someone,
僕も誰かに尋ねることが
できる日がくるとしたら
then someday,
いつか
その目に映ってきた景色を
the scenery reflected in those eyes...
The stories that exist on the other side of the storm...
嵐の向こうにあるものの話を
そう—
That's right.
I still don't know the stories that are told on the other side of the goal.
ゴールの向こう側について語られる
物語を 僕はまだ知らない
Child of God (Part Three)
Important Things. Important Matters.
U-Um...
え ええっと…
そろそろ ごはんにしようか
Maybe we should have dinner?
Y-Yeah...
Right now, Hina is extremely nervous.
（零）ヒナちゃんは今
猛烈に緊張している
Normally she's energetic like a ball of light,
ふだんは パーっと
元気になったり
or dejected like a dark cloud,
シューンと
しょんぼりしたり
or angry like a bolt of lightning.
ムキーって怒ったり
She's lively, in more ways than one.
いろんな意味で活発であり
I think of it as a good characteristic of hers.
そこが 彼女の持ち味であると
思うのだけど
But she's currently as stiff as a board.
その彼女が固まっている
And that's because in front of her,
なぜなら目の前に
高橋君が いるからである
Takahashi is right there.
Nervous
Freeze
Man, it's been a while since I've come here.
いやー 久しぶりだな 川本んち
Nervous
Freeze
小２のとき以来？
Since second grade?
Nervous
Freeze
Um, Hina?
Nervous
あの ヒナちゃん？
Freeze
Nervous
Hey, let's have curry already.
（川本モモ）ねえねえ
カレー 早く食べよう
Nervous
Freeze
Ughhh
Ahhhh
Come on, Hina. Get it together.
（零）ほら
ヒナちゃん しっかり
Is this enough rice?
ごはん こんくらいでいい？
Do you think curry will be enough?
（ひなた）ほんとに
カレーでよかったのかな
Maybe a fancier dinner would've been better.
あっ やっぱり もっと
豪華なごはんのほうが
よかったんじゃないのかな
Curry is too ordinary.
カレーなんて
ありきたりすぎだよ
喜んでくれないよ
It won't make him happy!
（零）大丈夫だよ
上手に出来てるよ
It'll be fine.
It came out really well.
You have 1 new message
Inbox
Takahashi
It's Takahashi.
Are you free on Saturday, Kiriyama?
高橋君から
I just got a message from Takahashi, asking if I'm free on Saturday.
“土曜空いてますか”って
メール来たんだけど
Can we both go to your house, Hina?
ヒナちゃんちに
一緒に行っていいかな？
キャー！
Fuhpoof
Um...
I feel kind of bad now about making her so nervous.
（零）何か悪かったかな
こんなに緊張させて
Rei, I'm hungry.
（モモ）零ちゃーん
モモ おなかすいた
（零）何か悪かったかな
こんなに緊張させて
No way! Why aren't you going to be home Saturday night, Sis?!
うそ！ えっ？ 何で お姉ちゃん
土曜の夜いないの？
I asked him to eat dinner with us!
晩ごはん一緒にどうぞって
言っちゃったよ
This is problematic.
困ったわね うーん
I was suddenly asked to work at the store on Saturday.
土曜は 急に
お店番 頼まれちゃって
Let's see...
そうねえ あ！
じゃあ カレーにすれば？
Why don't you make curry?
You can make it in advance and just warm it up when he gets here. Easy, right?
先に作っておけば
あとは来てから
温めるだけで安心でしょ？
No worries about messing up, either.
そしたら失敗とかも無いし
えーっ！ 普通っぽすぎる
But that's too ordinary!
It has to be, let's see, fancier and more elaborate!
もっと もっとこう—
豪華なっていうか
凝った感じのヤツでないと
You haven't learned your lesson at all, have you?
（あかり）
あなた まだ懲りてないようね
Have you forgotten about the lunch box already?
お弁当のときの事 忘れたの？
もう だから…
ごはんというのはね
Sheesh...
Look, when it comes to making dinner...
Ping!
（シロちゃん）ごはん？
What?! Dinner?! Did you just say dinner?!
（ミケちゃん）何すか？ 何すか？
今 ごはんって言いましたよね？
なあ おい！
Right?!
Yeah, I totally heard it!
（シロちゃん）ええ 先輩！
自分も確かに聞いたっス！
Oh, no! The "dinner" I'm talking about isn't your "dinner"...
ああっ しまった！
違うの
今 言ったごはんは
あなたたちの
ごはんのことじゃなくって
Oh, I just said it twice!
あ また２回も言っちゃった
Dinner?! Dinner?! Sis, are you making our dinner?!
（クロちゃん）
ごはんすか ごはんすか？
お姉さん ごはんなんですかー？
Snack
（シロちゃん）うめえニャー
Nom nom
Meow
Looks like
she lost...
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
Nom nom
Meow
Delicious
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
Nom nom
Meow
Delicious
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
Meow
Meroweow
Delicious
O-Okay, then how about deep-fried chicken as an extra topping?
Nom nom
Meow
Delicious
Nom nom
Meow
Meroweow
じゃあ おまけで
から揚げをトッピング
ってのは どうよ？
Curry
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Curry
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Curry
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Curry
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Curry
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
から揚げ
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Deep-fried...
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Super tasty
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Super tasty
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Super tasty
(Tasty)
Deep-fried Chicken
Super tasty
And what would you say to adding a hot spring egg on top of that?
（あかり）そして 更に
温泉卵をのっけるっていうのは？
Well?!
Super tasty
温泉卵までも？
A hot spring egg too?!
Tasty
Mega tasty
ははぁ〜っ
（零）おおっ まとまったようだ
Looks like that's settled.
Phew
で 高橋君は というと
And as for Takahashi...
あっ 温泉卵がのってる
There's a hot spring egg on top.
Thump
Got effected by it
いただきまーす
Thump
Thank you for the meal!
いーたーだーきます
Thump
ああ すっごい
気持ちのいい食べっぷり
He's eating it in such a delicious way.
Your guys' curry is awesome!
川本んちのカレーってすごいな
The deep-fried chicken topping alone is great, but then hot spring egg too? Pretty fancy!
から揚げだけでも すげえのに
しかも温泉卵がのってるなんて
超豪華じゃんか
It's like I'm at a restaurant!
お店で食うやつみたいだ
Really?!
（ひなた）ほんと？
お代わりもあるよ
You can have seconds too!
Yes! Thank you, Sis!
（ひなた）よかったー
お姉ちゃんありがとう
Oh, that's right.
あ そうだ
I wanted to ask you something, Kiriyama.
俺 桐山さんに
聞きたいことあるんすけど
Kawamoto, can I borrow your VCR?
川本 ビデオデッキ借りていい？
S-Sure.
あっ いいよ
えっと これなんスけど
Um... it's this.
B-Bodoro!
That's the guy who came over last time!
（ひなた）わぁ こないだ来た人だ
（モモ）ボドロ！
Wh-Wh-Why?!
な 何で？
What? Nikaidou, 4-dan, has been here too?
えっ 何？
二海堂四段も 来たことあるの？
Incredible!
すげえ
I-Incredible?
すごい？
He's a person on TV?
テレビに出る人だったの？
He never said anything like that.
何も そんなこと
言ってなかったよ
あっ そっか
親友ですもんね 桐山さん
Oh, I see.
He's your best friend, right, Kiriyama?
Best friend?
（零）親友？
H-How did it get to that?
な 何で
そんなことになってんの？
（高橋）仲いいんですよね？
You two are close, huh?
Nikaidou often says that, in interviews and stuff.
二海堂さん よく言ってますもんね
インタビューとかで
ちょっと待てよ
二海堂が解説ってことは…
Wait a second. If Nikaidou is commentating...
あ… ねえ このビデオ
また今度にしない？
Hey, why don't we save this video for next time?
Black, G-6f.
（棋譜読み上げ）
先手 ６六金
後手 ３四角成
White, B-3d+.
Black, +B-6d.
（棋譜読み上げ）
先手 ６四馬
（記録係）
桐山五段 残り７分です
Kiriyama, 5-dan, has seven minutes remaining.
Um... thank you for dinner.
（零）えーっと…
ごちそうさまでした
Wh-What?!
R-R-Rei!
（ひなた）
ねっ ねっ！ 零ちゃん
何でテレビに映ってんの？
Rei, no run away!
Why are you on TV?!
Momo, you're heavy...
将棋って
部活って言ってたよね
You said you're in a shogi club at school, right?!
Oh shoot.
（高橋）
あ そっか… しまった
Crap. I didn't know Kiriyama was keeping it a secret.
やべっ 桐山さん
内緒にしてたんだっけ
（川本相米二(そめじ)）
うん 何だ坊主 情報解禁か？
What's up, kid? Your secret's been disclosed?
Hello. Thank you for having me.
（高橋）
あっ どうも お邪魔してます
Hey, Takahashi's kid.
おお 高橋のせがれか？
でっかくなったなあ
You've gotten big!
How's your old man and granddad?
くそじじいと
くそ親父は元気か？
They're both well, sir.
（勇介）はい 元気っス
夕べも
将棋指してケンカしてました
They were playing shogi and fighting over it just last night.
あ で 桐山五段に
聞いてこいって言われたんスけど
So they wanted me to ask Kiriyama, 5-dan, a question.
（相米二）おおっ？ ＮＨＫ杯？
The NHK Cup?
Which part? I was watching it too.
どこだ？ 俺も見てたぞ
（高橋）あ ここです
Oh, it's right here.
（棋譜読み上げ）
先手 ４二馬
Black, +Bx4b.
What?! What are you doing, Kiriyama?!
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）えっ？ わーっ
何てことするんだ 桐山！
I don't know if he went in for the kill or to be killed!
これじゃ
“切り”に行ったのか
“切られ”に行ったのか
分からんだろー！
Nikaidou, 4-dan? Nikaidou, 4-dan?
Now that's some passionate commentary!
（相米二）
熱い解説だな おい
My dad and grandpa said they didn't think that was the losing move.
じいちゃんも親父も—
これが敗着の一手だったとは
思えないって
They wondered what Nikaidou, 4-dan, was going on about.
二海堂四段は—
何でこんなこと言ってるんだ
って
White, K-x4b.
（棋譜読み上げ）
同玉 先手 ５五金
Black, Gx5e.
No, he's right.
いいえ 彼の言うとおり
これが敗着の一手でした
That was the losing move.
Seems like
he lost...
Dad and Grandpa didn't think the move was that bad.
（高橋）
じいちゃんも親父も これが
そんなに悪手とは思えない
In fact, they said it felt like an
aggressive move with manly spirit.
むしろ 攻めっ気と
男気にあふれた手な気がするって
After my opponent surrounded me,
he didn't attack and waited for me to make a mistake.
相手が ガッチガチに
堅く囲って—
俺のミス待ちで
全然 動かないから 何か…
So I thought, "All right, let's see if this is a mistake or not."
じゃあ ミスするかどうか
やってやろうじゃないかって思って
Don't try to act cool, Kiriyama!
（二海堂）かっこつけんな 桐山！
If you really want to win, then persevere!
NHK Cup
Tournament
本当に勝ちたいんなら粘れ！
攻めるだけじゃなく
ちゃんと守れ！
Don't just attack, you have to defend!
You've been acting a little weird lately!
最近のお前
ちょっと変だぞ！
Nikaidou, we can't see the board!
（聞き手）二海堂さん
盤面が見えません！
（二海堂）
三段リーグの頃のお前のほうが
もっと慎重でひたむきだった
You used to be more careful and single-minded back in the 3-dan league!
潔いのと 投げやりなのは
似ているけど違うんだー！
Bravery and recklessness are similar but different!
（聞き手）
もうちょっと こちらのほうに
桐山！ 聞こえてるか？
Kiriyama, can you hear me?!
Nikaidou, 4-dan, you're too close to the camera!
（聞き手）二海堂四段
カメラ 近すぎます
Take better care of your shogi, and yourself, Kiriyama!
もっと自分の将棋を—
自分を大切にしてくれ
桐山！
You're way too close!
（聞き手）ああっ…
ドアップ過ぎます
二海堂四段 対局室は４階です
聞こえませんてば
They're playing on the 4th floor.
He can't hear you! Please calm down!
落ち着いてください
（相米二）ふーん
だとさ 坊主
You heard him, kid.
You got yourself a good friend there.
おめえ なかなか
いい友達 持ってんじゃねえかい
I'm a little envious.
俺 ちょっとうらやましいです
（二海堂）親友として
あえて言わせてもらう
I'm saying this as your best friend!
Your best friend, he says!
（相米二）親友だってさ！
Ah, youth! I'm jealous, dammit!
青春ぽいっじゃねえか
こんちきしょう
（ひなた）はら〜っ
（モモ）ボドロー！
Bodoro...
Listen! I'm only going to say this once!
いいか 一度しか言わん！
But it's kind of important.
ああ でも大事なことだぞ
いいか桐山 だからむしろ
ビデオにとって何度も見ろ！
Listen, Kiriyama!
In fact, get this on video so you can watch it over and over again!
（相米二）いや〜 いいなー
Wow, that's amazing.
（高橋）さすがマブダチっすね
They're BFFs after all.
Take better care of yourself!
自分を大切にしろ！
The reason why you can't progress is because you're not doing that!
それができないのが
伸び悩みの原因だ
Dammit! Like you'd know!
くっそ！ 知るか！
Who the hell do you think you are?!
何だよ その 上から目線
Explode
ムカつくなあ くそぉ！
That really pisses me off, god damn it!
Explode
零ちゃん
Rei!
ほお？ 坊主が怒った
The kid's angry!
In the first place, what he's saying is crazy!
（零）大体 この人
言ってることがおかしいよ
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"I'm only going to say this once!
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
So record it and watch it over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
"I'm only going
to say this once!"
"So record it and watch it
over and over again!"
もう全然
意味分かんないんスけど！
I don't understand it at all!
Good point!
（高橋）ああ 確かに
But I think Nikaidou's feelings for you as his best friend are genuine!
でも 二海堂さんの
親友を思う気持ちは
俺 本物だと思うっス
（相米二）キャー
甘酸っぱいぜ お前ら
Wheee-ooo, you guys are sweet and sour!
今時の若いもんも
捨てたもんじゃねえなあ ハハハ…
There's hope for this generation yet!
Haaaa
いいなあ
Lucky!
Lucky?! What the hell is?!
えっ？ 一体どこが？
うふふ
零ちゃんのでっかい声
初めて聞いた
This is the first time I've heard you raise your voice, Rei!
（零）彼女の言葉に
Her words...
surprised me a little.
僕は ちょっぴり驚いた
This is kind of fun.
（ひなた）何か 楽しいね
（零）だって
After all, nobody had ever said that to me before.
そんなこと言われたの
初めてだったんだ
Hey, Rei.
（ひなた）ねえ 零ちゃんお願い
Would you please teach me how to play shogi?
私にも 将棋教えてくれる？
Important Things. Important Matters.
Teach Me How to Play Shogi
Would you teach me how to play shogi?
私にも 将棋教えてくれる？
（零）知らなかった
I had no idea.
If someone had interest in a world I was a part of,
誰かに
自分のいる世界のことについて
興味を持ってもらえることが
こんなにも—
I didn't know it would make my stomach feel fluffy and make me happy.
おなかの辺りが ふわふわするほど
うれしいことだったなんて
Let's see...
（零）えーっと まず
盤は どれにしようか
First, what kind of board should we go with?
A plastic mat would probably be better than a wooden board.
木製よりビニールマットのほうが
いいかもな
お茶の間の ちゃぶ台の
上に乗せるわけだから
Since it'll be used on the table in the living room.
And maybe we should use these plastic pieces,
since they're easy to handle.
で 駒も
気軽に扱ってもらえるように
このプラスチックのが いいかも
Besides, Momo often spills milk.
モモちゃん
牛乳とか よくこぼすし
Ahhh!
Splash
My milk!
Water of life
Zoom
Meow
The writing on the pieces isn't in cursive, so it's easy to read.
字も崩してないから
読みやすいし
あっ あと一応
And maybe we should have an illustrated guide to make it easier to understand.
図解とかあったほうが
分かりいいかな？
Hm, which one would be good?
えーっと…
どれがいいかな
I recommend Taniyama and Senzaki for beginners, as they're easy to understand.
（二海堂）初心者向けなら—
谷山先生と千咲(せんざき)先生のが
分かりやすいぞ
N-Nikaidou?
えっ？ 二海堂？
Boing
Shucks. They're sold out.
うむ 品切れだな
残念至極
That's too bad.
あの これください
Um, I'll take this.
I'm thrilled, Kiriyama!
うれしいよ 桐山
Passionate
Clench
You sense the importance of spreading the word too!
Passionate
Clench
君も普及の大切さを
感じてるんだね
Passionate
Clench
Sparkle
If it's okay with you, can I help?
You don't have to, but if you really
wanted, I could totally help you!
If it's okay with you, can I help?
You don't have to, but if you really
wanted, I could totally help you!
Sparkle
So, who are you going to teach?
で 誰に教えるんだい？
Sparkle
Well then!
（ひなた）では
よろしくお願いします
Please take care of us!
Looks like he lost from
the pressure, passion,
and many other things...
Looks like he lost from
the pressure, passion,
and many other things...
（モモ）します
Please!
Yay, Bododo!
No problem. The pleasure is mine.
（二海堂）
うむ こちらこそよろしく
Bododo
Baaam
I hope it'll be okay.
（ひなた）大丈夫かな？
覚えられるかなあ 私にも
Sniff
I hope I can remember everything.
Don't worry!
大丈夫
難しそうに見えるけど
It looks difficult, but it's surprisingly simple to begin.
Bododo
Smile
始めるのは
意外に簡単なんだよ
もし 難しく感じたとしたら
If you do feel that it's difficult, Hina, it won't be your fault.
Looks like he lost from
the pressure, passion,
and many other things...
Looks like he lost from
the pressure, passion,
and many other things...
Bododo
それはヒナちゃんのせいじゃなく
全て教えた人間の責任だから
Bododo
The person who's teaching you is fully responsible.
And so,
good luck, Mr. Kiriyama!
というわけで はい
桐山先生 お願いします
Slap
What? It's my turn after a lead-in like that?
え？ そんな前振りから
俺のターンに？
Shock
Okay. I'll give you a simple explanation.
えーっとですね
シンプルに説明すると
On top of this board made of nine rows and nine columns,
この 縦９×横９の
81マスの盤の上で
お互い ８種類
20枚ずつの駒を使い—
you and your opponent both use 20 pieces of eight different types.
駒を取ったり取られたりしながら
相手の王様を捕まえるゲームです
During the game, you trade pieces back and forth,
but the main point is to capture your opponent's king.
The person who goes first is black, the second person is white, and then you alternate turns.
先に指す人が“先手”
後に指す人が“後手”といって
交互に一手ずつ指していきます
Each of the eight different types of pieces
has its own strengths and range of movement.
８種類の駒は
それぞれ性格が違って
動ける範囲が異なります
Incidentally, the columns are called "files" and the rows are called "ranks."
ちなみに この 縦の列が“筋”
横の列を“段”
The rows are marked with numerals.
通常 横を
算用数字で記します
And all of the boxes have an address.
で マス目には
１つずつ住所があって
Next, I'll explain how each piece can move.
で 次は １つ１つの
駒の動かし方ですが…
（二海堂）
ちょーっと待て 桐山
Wait a second, Kiriyama!
Pull
堅っ！
That's stiff! You're too stiff, Kiriyama!
堅いよ 桐山
（ひなた）えーっと えーっと
Um... Um...
Um...
Write
Her expression says, "Hm, maybe this is difficult after all."
Um...
（二海堂）ほら
もう ヒナくん—
Um...
Write
Black goes first...
Um...
Write
うーん やっぱり難しいかも
って顔に なっているだろう？
Um...
Write
Hey, Hina, I'd like some yogurt.
Um...
She'll be so nervous, it'll all go in one ear and out the other!
ああいうふうになると 緊張して
頭に入りにくくなってしまうんだ
Um...
White goes second...
It'll just be a waste.
それじゃ
もったいないだろう？
You have to make the first impression easily understandable.
最初のイメージだけでも
つかみやすくしないと
Th-Then what should I do?
（零）じゃ… じゃあ
どうするのさ
All right, Hina and Momo!
さあ ヒナ君 モモ君
今度は 僕が説明しよう
This time, I'll explain!
Shogi for Beginners Picture Book
Drawn and Written by Nikaidou Harunobu
Okay, let's look at this picture book together.
さあ この絵本を一緒に見よう
Shogi for Beginners Picture Book
Drawn and Written by Nikaidou Harunobu
Shiny
All right!
はい！
Ha-meow
... .. . .. .. ... .. .. ... ..
Oh, kitties!
Hungry
わっ ニャーちゃんだ
王様もいるよ
There's a king too.
All different kinds of kitties!
いろんなニャーがいる
Hungry
将棋っていうのは
こんなふうに
Shogi is a game in which you use eight
different types of personality and pieces
８種類の性格の違う
駒を動かして
like this to capture your opponent's king.
相手の王様を捕まえるゲームなんだ
You play on this board of 81 squares made up of nine rows and columns.
ゲームは この９×９の
81マスの上でやるんだ
The three rows of pieces in front of you is your land.
手前の３段が 自分の国
Your Army
The three rows on the other side are from your opponent's land.
向こう３段が 相手の国だ
Enemy Army
Next I'll introduce the personalities of each type of cat.
（二海堂）さあ
では 次は—
Meow
一人一人の
ニャーたちの性格を紹介するぞ
Meow
Okay!
（モモ）はい
（ひなた）お願いします
Please do!
うむ いい返事だ
Yes! Good responses.
Nikaidou... you're amazing.
（零）二海堂 お前 すげえよ
What is this feeling I have?
何だろう？ この気持ち
Answer:           Exclusion
Teach Me How to Play Shogi
Cat Shogi Sing-along
Let's learn how to play shogi with cats!
You're a hard worker who moves ahead one space at a time
You may be the weakest piece, but your paw delivers a punch
That's the pawn in shogi!
Next up is the knight!
You hop around left and right because you can move diagonally a little
You can jump over friend and enemy alike, and your kangaroo punch is like an explosion
That's the knight in shogi!
Next up is the gold general!
You protect the king like a bodyguard
You also go to the enemy king because that's where you love to be
That's what the gold general does in shogi! And now you know how to play shogi!
Next Episode Preview
Episode 8
（ひなた）ええっ？
すごい 本当に？ すてき
Wow! Really?! That's wonderful!
（零）
うっ 何ですって？
What?!
（花岡(はなおか)）坊ちゃま
素晴らしい出来でございます
It came out wonderfully, Young Master!
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）二海堂！
お前ってヤツは
Nikaidou! I can't believe you!
Oh no. I'm going to cry!
（三角龍雪(みすみたつゆき)）
やばい 俺 泣きそう
You noticed!
（二海堂）
気づいてくれたか？
（モモ）
肉球パンチおみまいするニャ
I'll deliver you my paw-punch!
Illustration: Chiba Tetsuya
（ひなた）３月のライオン
次回も見てね
Please watch the next episode of "March comes in like a lion" too!
Shogi is fun! Let's all try it together!
将棋 面白いよ
みんなも一緒にやってみよう！